<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Algorithms on Ian Michael Trotter</title>
    <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/tags/algorithms/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Algorithms on Ian Michael Trotter</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Ian Michael Trotter</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://www.iantrotter.com/tags/algorithms/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Reverse the Curse: Can Quantum Computing Lift Bellman’s Curse of Dimensionality?</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/project/reverse-the-curse/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/project/reverse-the-curse/</guid>
      <description>Introduction The purpose of this research is to develop improved methods for the numerical resolution of stochastic dynamic optimisation problems. Although Bellman’s infamous “curse of dimensionality” impedes the numerical resolution of many such problems, approximation methods have had considerable success. At the same time, the quantum computing paradigm could revolutionise the resolution of optimisation problems.
Can we leverage the combined power of approximation methods and quantum computing in order to improve performance and enable the resolution of larger instances of such problems than is currently possible?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accelerating Numerical Stochastic Dynamic Optimisation for Applied Economics</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/project/accelerating-sdp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/project/accelerating-sdp/</guid>
      <description>Stochastic dynamic optimisation problems are found in several branches of economics: consumer theory, producer theory, resource economics, macroeconomics, game theory, operations research, and so forth. And most of the time, the numerical resolution of these problems is considered computationally intractable due to the so-called &amp;ldquo;curse of dimensionality&amp;rdquo;.
The main goal of this project is to develop new computational methods for the numerical resolution of stochastic dynamic optimisation problems. Improved techniques for resolving this problem class could have a great impact on society, as it would improve decision support systems for a large number of institutions, and for instance improve the management of natural resources, adaptation to and mitigation of climate change, financial management and business decisions.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>