<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ian Michael Trotter on Ian Michael Trotter</title>
    <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ian Michael Trotter on Ian Michael Trotter</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Ian Michael Trotter</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2017 23:00:00 -0300</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Developing the Norwegian Energy System in the European Energy Transition (NORENS)</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/project/norens/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/project/norens/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The primary objective of NORENS is to develop a broader and better knowlegde base for the problem of planning an efficient, profitable and robust electricity production and transmission infrastructure for Norway in light of the ongoing transition of the European energy system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project is a collaboration between researchers at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nmbu.no/en/faculty/mina&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Faculty of Environmental Sciences and Natural Resource Management (MINA)&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nmbu.no/en/faculty/hh&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;School of Economics and Business&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nmbu.no/en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Norwegian University of Life Sciences&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cicero.uio.no/en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Center for International Climate Research&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uio.no/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;University of Oslo&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dtu.dk/english&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Technical University of Denmark (DTU)&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ufv.br/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Federal University of Viçosa&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uni-oldenburg.de/en/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;University of Oldenburg&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nve.no/english/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The Norwegian Water Resources and Energy Directorate (NVE)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, the project is backed by a number of industrial partners &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.statnett.no/en/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Statnett&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nve.no/english/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The Norwegian Water Resources and Energy Directorate (NVE)&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ostfoldenergi.no/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Østfold Energi&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; and is supported by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forskningsradet.no/prognett-energix/Home_page/1253980140022&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ENERGIX programme&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forskningsradet.no/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Norwegian Research Council&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reverse the Curse: Can Quantum Computing Lift Bellman’s Curse of Dimensionality?</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/project/reverse-the-curse/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/project/reverse-the-curse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this research is to develop improved methods for the numerical resolution of stochastic dynamic optimisation problems. Although Bellman’s infamous “curse of dimensionality” impedes the numerical resolution of all but the simplest such problems, approximation methods have had considerable success. At the same time, recent research shows that the quantum computing paradigm could revolutionise the resolution of optimisation problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, no research appears yet to have considered the application of quantum computing to stochastic dynamic optimisation problems. This research proposes the development of new algorithms that leverage the power of both approximation methods and quantum computing, in order to improve performance and enable the resolution of larger instances of such problems than is currently possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project is supported by &lt;a href=&#34;https://serrapilheira.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Instituto Serrapilheira&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accelerating Numerical Stochastic Dynamic Optimisation for Applied Economics</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/project/accelerating-sdp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/project/accelerating-sdp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Stochastic dynamic optimisation problems are found in several branches of economics: consumer theory, producer theory, resource economics, macroeconomics, game theory, operations research, and so forth. And most of the time, the numerical resolution of these problems is considered computationally intractable due to the so-called &amp;ldquo;curse of dimensionality&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main goal of this project is to develop new computational methods for the numerical resolution of stochastic dynamic optimisation problems. Improved techniques for resolving this problem class could have a great impact on society, as it would improve decision support systems for a large number of institutions, and for instance improve the management of natural resources, adaptation to and mitigation of climate change, financial management and business decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project is supported by FAPEMIG.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Phd Thesis Won an Award</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/phd-thesis-award/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/phd-thesis-award/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On wednesday last week, the winners of the awards (one per field) for &lt;a href=&#34;http://capes.gov.br/sala-de-imprensa/noticias/8592-premio-capes-seleciona-melhores-teses-defendidas-em-2016&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;best PhD theses in Brazil in 2016 were announced&lt;/a&gt;. And, lo and behold, there was &lt;a href=&#34;http://capes.gov.br/images/stories/download/legislacao/Portaria-199-Premio-Capes-de-Tese-2017.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;my name in the official gazette&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; receiving the award in the field of economics for my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iantrotter.com/files/Thesis_Ian_Trotter.pdf&#34;&gt;thesis on energy and climate change&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I am grateful for receiving some recognition for all the hard work that went into the thesis. As anyone who has done a PhD probably knows: it takes dedication, a lot of elbow grease and many sleepless nights to complete a PhD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I appreciate the opportunity to draw some additional attention to my own research, and to the excellent research of my friends and colleagues, as well as to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.poseconomiaaplicada.ufv.br/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;my graduate program&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.der.ufv.br/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;my department&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ufv.br/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;my institution&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even so, however, I am wary of awards in science, which might be an attitude I picked from reading Dr. Richard Feynman&amp;rsquo;s autobiography when I was in high school. Mainly there are two reasons why I&amp;rsquo;m not such a great fan of awards in science:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, science is &amp;ndash; directly or indirectly &amp;ndash; a collaborative effort. Even if the scientist receiving the award may not have been working on a team, we are all standing on shoulders of giants and our work has been enabled by those who came before us. To bestow an award only on the scientist who happened to dot the i&amp;rsquo;s and cross the t&amp;rsquo;s, one is perhaps not paying sufficient attention to the entire foundation on which the work rests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, there is no way to objectively compare works against each other and rank them, especially so shortly after publication, and I find it slightly pretentious to pretend to have that ability. The impact or importance of a discovery is often only obvious after many years, sometimes decades or centuries. In this sense, awards are more reminiscent of a popularity contest than a science contest, rewarding only those contributions whose impacts are immediately obvious and recognised (usually because they are uncontroversial and not too far from the dominating view of the time). Science already advances one funeral at the time, according to Planck, and handing out awards to those whose discoveries conform to expectations will help perpetuate scientific orthodoxy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, though, awards in science seem relatively harmless. Sometimes it is worthwhile to pay a particular homage to the anchor of the relay race of science. And so what if not all awarded discoveries age that well? That appears to happen to all types of awards (e.g. Titanic). It&amp;rsquo;s still a great opportunity to make some fanfare, drum up some positive press, celebrate our collective achievements and, perhaps, increase the overall interest in science.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PAEG</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/project/paeg/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/project/paeg/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Website Launched!</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/website-launch/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2017 09:09:02 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/website-launch/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to my researcher profile website! This site will showcase my research, showing both results and work in progress. It feels a little empty at the moment, but it will gradually fill up with interesting content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The site was hacked together in a relatively short time using the following components:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Built with &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/gcushen/hugo-academic&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Academic theme&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hosted on &lt;a href=&#34;https://pages.github.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Fiscal Policy: A Dynamic Analysis for Brazil</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/publication/optimal-fiscal-policy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/publication/optimal-fiscal-policy/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Soil and altitude drives diversity and functioning of Brazilian (Campo de Altitude)</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/publication/diversity_drivers/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/publication/diversity_drivers/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimal LNG (liquefied natural gas) regasification scheduling for import terminals with storage</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/publication/optimal-regasification/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/publication/optimal-regasification/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate Change and Electricity Demand in Brazil: A Stochastic Approach</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/publication/electricity-demand/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/publication/electricity-demand/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
