<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ian Michael Trotter on Ian Michael Trotter</title>
    <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ian Michael Trotter on Ian Michael Trotter</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Ian Michael Trotter</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2017 23:00:00 -0300</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Computational Tricks for Numeric Stochastic Dynamic Programming: Solving a Large Example with (Relative Ease)</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/talk/ppgea-sept18/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Aug 2018 11:35:02 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/talk/ppgea-sept18/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>30th International Seminar on Economic Policy</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/xxx-sipe/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Aug 2018 10:45:46 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/xxx-sipe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m on the organising committee of the 30th International Seminar on Economic Policy (SIPE), the 13th and 14th of September, 2018. SIPE is an annual event at the Department of Agricultural Economics, UFV. Fot the 30th anniversary, the event will be especially great, with the main theme being &amp;ldquo;Sustainability and Perspectives for the Brazilian Agriculture&amp;rdquo;. Certainly, there will be much interesting discussion around the latest Brazilian agricultural census that has just been released, and plenty of other interesting topics related to the future of Brazilian agriculture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, I will be hosting a session on some futuristic topics: Intelligent Agriculture, Bioeconomy and Bioenergy &amp;ndash; at 08:00 on Friday 14th of September &amp;ndash; featuring some great speakers: Silvia Maria Fonseca Massruhá from EMBRAPA will talk about intelligent agriculture (which we all know is the future of agriculture), and Amaro Olímpio Pereira Junior &amp;ndash; which will talk about bioenergy (which we all know is the future of energy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone is welcome!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the full program, and for signing up, please visit the link: (&lt;a href=&#34;http://bit.ly/30SIPE&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://bit.ly/30SIPE&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing community trees using the open tree of life increases the reliability of phylogenetic diversity and dispersion indices</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/publication/community-trees/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Aug 2018 23:31:56 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/publication/community-trees/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The rule of 72</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/rule-of-72/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2018 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/rule-of-72/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;rule of 72&amp;rdquo; is &amp;ndash; or at least should be &amp;ndash; a standard tool in everyone&amp;rsquo;s mathematical toolkit, and helps us think intuitively about exponential growth and exponential decay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But did you ever stop and wonder how and why this black magic incantation actually works?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rule of 72 says that if you divide the number 72 by the percentage growth rate, you will get approximately the time to double or the half time. Suppose, for instance, that the population growth rate is 2% per year. To calculate approximately how long time it will take for the population to double, we simply divide 72 by the growth rate in percent:
$$ \text{Years to double} = \frac{72}{2} = 36$$
A growth rate of 3% gives a doubling time of 24 years, 4% gives 18 years, 6% gives 12 years, and so on. In the case of exponential decay, the rule will give the half-time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an absolutely incredible approximation rule. It gives you superpowers: you are now able to simply glance quickly at a growth or decay rate and immediately get a feel for the doubling or halving time, which is often a more intuitive measure than the rate itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how does it work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First we set up an equation showing exactly what we mean by doubling time, and how it relates to the rate of (compounded) growth. If $p$ is the growth rate and $a_0$ is the initial quantity, we know that after one period, the quantity $a_1$ will be given by:
$$ a_1 = a_0(1+p). $$
To calculate the quantity after two periods, we apply the growth rate to $a_1$:
$$ a_2 = a_1(1+p) = a_0 (1+p)(1+p) = a_0(1+p)^2. $$
You&amp;rsquo;ve probably got the point already: after applying the growth rate for $n$ periods, the quantity will be:
$$ a_n = a_0(1+p)^n. $$
If we are looking for the doubling time, we want to know how many periods it takes before the quantity has grown to twice its initial value, $2a_0$. In fact, we want to know the number of periods $n$ such that:
$$ 2a_0 = a_0(1+p)^n. $$
Solving this equation for the number $n$ is not so hard: first we can divide both sides by $a_0$ to make it disappear entirely from the equation (it turns out that the doubling time does not depend on the initial quantity!), and then we take the natural logarithm of both sides of the equation and simply solve for $n$:
$$ 2 = (1+p)^n $$
$$ \ln(2) = n\ln(1+p) $$
$$ n = \frac{\ln(2)}{\ln(1+p)} $$
This equation explicitly gives the &lt;em&gt;exact&lt;/em&gt; number of periods $n$ that the initial quantity will take to double, given the growth rate $p$. But as a rule-of-thumb, it would be very handy, because it involves calculating two logarithms and doing a division, which is too taxing for my poor little head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So from here, we make two wonderful approximations. Firstly, we note that when the growth rate $p$ is small, we can approximate $\ln(1+p)$ simply by $p$:
$$ \ln(1+p) \approx p. $$
You can try this on your calculator, and see that it is a fairly accurate approximation for small values of $p$, up to about $0.1$ (that is, a 10% growth rate).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But wait a minute &amp;ndash; how did we do that? And how can we be sure that it is so? Testing things on the calculator may convince some people, but certainly not a critical mind. And furthermore, I don&amp;rsquo;t find it to be a very satisfactory explanation. So let&amp;rsquo;s make the argument a little more convincing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few prerequisites: we all know that the derivative of $\ln(x)$ is simply $1/x$. And we also know that $\ln(1)=0$. A &amp;ldquo;first-order &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taylor_series&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Taylor expansion&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; is a way of approximating the value of a function at a point using the value of the function and its derivative at a nearby point:
$$ f(x_0 + \Delta x) \approx f(x_0) + f&amp;rsquo;(x_0) \Delta x. $$
Now, let&amp;rsquo;s try creating a first-order Taylor expansion of the function $\ln(x)$ around the point $x_0=1$:
$$ \ln(1+\Delta x) \approx \ln(1) + \frac{1}{1}\Delta x. $$
Then remember that $\ln(1)=0$, and use $\Delta x = p$:
$$ \ln(1+p) \approx p. $$
So this approximation is simply the first-order Taylor expansion of the natural logarithm $\ln(\cdot)$ around the point $x_0 = 1$! (If you are concerned about the accuracy of the approximation, rest assured that it will be of the order $O(p^2)$.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the doubling time. Insert the first wonderful approximation $\ln(1+p) \approx p$ into the denominator:
$$ n \approx \frac{\ln(2)}{p}. $$
Calculating $\ln(2)$ can be a little tricky too, so let&amp;rsquo;s try to do something about the numerator. Calculating $\ln(2)$ to the first ten decimal points gives the following:
$$ \ln(2) = 0.6931471806 = 69.31471806\% $$
Since the numerator is constant, let&amp;rsquo;s just put in a number that&amp;rsquo;s close to the number $\ln(2)$, but which is a little prettier and easier to work with. Since $p$ will normally assume values such as 1%, 2%, &amp;hellip;, it would be conventient to use a number that is easily divided by whole number percentages. Turns out that, amongst the numbers close to 69%, 72% is the number with the largest amount of prime factors &amp;ndash; which means that it can be evenly divided by many different integers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Number&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Factors&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Number of Factors&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;65&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5,13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;66&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,3,6,11,22,33&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;67&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;68&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,4,17,34&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;69&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3,23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;70&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,5,7,10,14,35&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;71&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;72&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2,3,4,6,8,9,12,18,24,36&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;73&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we choose 72% to approximate 69.31471806% in this case, because it is a number which is particularly easy to divide by many integers that we are likely to encounter (5, 7 and 10 being notable exceptions, but for that you can rather use 70 instead).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, we can approximate $n$ &amp;ndash; the number of periods required for doubling the initial quantity &amp;ndash; by:
$$ n \approx \frac{72}{p}. $$
And there you have it: the rule of 72. A simple approximation rule for thinking about growth (or decay) rates, supported by an interesting mathematical sleight-of-hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes we can solve a problem &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; correctly in a small fraction of the time it takes to solve the problem exactly. This post is an appreciation of approximation methods, related to my project on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iantrotter.com/project/reverse-the-curse/&#34;&gt;approximate solutions to stochastic dynamic optimisation problems&lt;/a&gt;, funded by &lt;a href=&#34;https://serrapilheira.org/en/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Instituto Serraphilheira&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Developing the Norwegian Energy System in the European Energy Transition (NORENS)</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/project/norens/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/project/norens/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The primary objective of NORENS is to develop a broader and better knowlegde base for the problem of planning an efficient, profitable and robust electricity production and transmission infrastructure for Norway in light of the ongoing transition of the European energy system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project is a collaboration between researchers at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nmbu.no/en/faculty/mina&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Faculty of Environmental Sciences and Natural Resource Management (MINA)&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nmbu.no/en/faculty/hh&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;School of Economics and Business&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nmbu.no/en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Norwegian University of Life Sciences&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cicero.uio.no/en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Center for International Climate Research&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uio.no/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;University of Oslo&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dtu.dk/english&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Technical University of Denmark (DTU)&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ufv.br/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Federal University of Viçosa&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uni-oldenburg.de/en/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;University of Oldenburg&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nve.no/english/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The Norwegian Water Resources and Energy Directorate (NVE)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, the project is backed by a number of industrial partners &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.statnett.no/en/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Statnett&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nve.no/english/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The Norwegian Water Resources and Energy Directorate (NVE)&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ostfoldenergi.no/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Østfold Energi&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; and is supported by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forskningsradet.no/prognett-energix/Home_page/1253980140022&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ENERGIX programme&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forskningsradet.no/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Norwegian Research Council&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reverse the Curse: Can Quantum Computing Lift Bellman’s Curse of Dimensionality?</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/project/reverse-the-curse/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/project/reverse-the-curse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this research is to develop improved methods for the numerical resolution of stochastic dynamic optimisation problems. Although Bellman’s infamous “curse of dimensionality” impedes the numerical resolution of all but the simplest such problems, approximation methods have had considerable success. At the same time, recent research shows that the quantum computing paradigm could revolutionise the resolution of optimisation problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, no research appears yet to have considered the application of quantum computing to stochastic dynamic optimisation problems. This research proposes the development of new algorithms that leverage the power of both approximation methods and quantum computing, in order to improve performance and enable the resolution of larger instances of such problems than is currently possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project is supported by &lt;a href=&#34;https://serrapilheira.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Instituto Serrapilheira&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accelerating Numerical Stochastic Dynamic Optimisation for Applied Economics</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/project/accelerating-sdp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/project/accelerating-sdp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Stochastic dynamic optimisation problems are found in several branches of economics: consumer theory, producer theory, resource economics, macroeconomics, game theory, operations research, and so forth. And most of the time, the numerical resolution of these problems is considered computationally intractable due to the so-called &amp;ldquo;curse of dimensionality&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main goal of this project is to develop new computational methods for the numerical resolution of stochastic dynamic optimisation problems. Improved techniques for resolving this problem class could have a great impact on society, as it would improve decision support systems for a large number of institutions, and for instance improve the management of natural resources, adaptation to and mitigation of climate change, financial management and business decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project is supported by FAPEMIG.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Phd Thesis Won an Award</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/phd-thesis-award/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/phd-thesis-award/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On wednesday last week, the winners of the awards (one per field) for &lt;a href=&#34;http://capes.gov.br/sala-de-imprensa/noticias/8592-premio-capes-seleciona-melhores-teses-defendidas-em-2016&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;best PhD theses in Brazil in 2016 were announced&lt;/a&gt;. And, lo and behold, there was &lt;a href=&#34;http://capes.gov.br/images/stories/download/legislacao/Portaria-199-Premio-Capes-de-Tese-2017.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;my name in the official gazette&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; receiving the award in the field of economics for my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iantrotter.com/files/Thesis_Ian_Trotter.pdf&#34;&gt;thesis on energy and climate change&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I am grateful for receiving some recognition for all the hard work that went into the thesis. As anyone who has done a PhD probably knows: it takes dedication, a lot of elbow grease and many sleepless nights to complete a PhD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I appreciate the opportunity to draw some additional attention to my own research, and to the excellent research of my friends and colleagues, as well as to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.poseconomiaaplicada.ufv.br/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;my graduate program&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.der.ufv.br/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;my department&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ufv.br/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;my institution&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even so, however, I am wary of awards in science, which might be an attitude I picked from reading Dr. Richard Feynman&amp;rsquo;s autobiography when I was in high school. Mainly there are two reasons why I&amp;rsquo;m not such a great fan of awards in science:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, science is &amp;ndash; directly or indirectly &amp;ndash; a collaborative effort. Even if the scientist receiving the award may not have been working on a team, we are all standing on shoulders of giants and our work has been enabled by those who came before us. To bestow an award only on the scientist who happened to dot the i&amp;rsquo;s and cross the t&amp;rsquo;s, one is perhaps not paying sufficient attention to the entire foundation on which the work rests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, there is no way to objectively compare works against each other and rank them, especially so shortly after publication, and I find it slightly pretentious to pretend to have that ability. The impact or importance of a discovery is often only obvious after many years, sometimes decades or centuries. In this sense, awards are more reminiscent of a popularity contest than a science contest, rewarding only those contributions whose impacts are immediately obvious and recognised (usually because they are uncontroversial and not too far from the dominating view of the time). Science already advances one funeral at the time, according to Planck, and handing out awards to those whose discoveries conform to expectations will help perpetuate scientific orthodoxy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, though, awards in science seem relatively harmless. Sometimes it is worthwhile to pay a particular homage to the anchor of the relay race of science. And so what if not all awarded discoveries age that well? That appears to happen to all types of awards (e.g. Titanic). It&amp;rsquo;s still a great opportunity to make some fanfare, drum up some positive press, celebrate our collective achievements and, perhaps, increase the overall interest in science.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PAEG</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/project/paeg/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/project/paeg/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Website Launched!</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/website-launch/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2017 09:09:02 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/website-launch/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to my researcher profile website! This site will showcase my research, showing both results and work in progress. It feels a little empty at the moment, but it will gradually fill up with interesting content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The site was hacked together in a relatively short time using the following components:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Built with &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/gcushen/hugo-academic&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Academic theme&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hosted on &lt;a href=&#34;https://pages.github.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Fiscal Policy: A Dynamic Analysis for Brazil</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/publication/optimal-fiscal-policy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/publication/optimal-fiscal-policy/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Soil and altitude drives diversity and functioning of Brazilian (Campo de Altitude)</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/publication/diversity_drivers/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/publication/diversity_drivers/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimal LNG (liquefied natural gas) regasification scheduling for import terminals with storage</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/publication/optimal-regasification/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/publication/optimal-regasification/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate Change and Electricity Demand in Brazil: A Stochastic Approach</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/publication/electricity-demand/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/publication/electricity-demand/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
