<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Ian Michael Trotter</title>
    <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Ian Michael Trotter</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Ian Michael Trotter</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://www.iantrotter.com/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>30th International Seminar on Economic Policy</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/xxx-sipe/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Aug 2018 10:45:46 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/xxx-sipe/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m on the organising committee of the 30th International Seminar on Economic Policy (SIPE), the 13th and 14th of September, 2018. SIPE is an annual event at the Department of Agricultural Economics, UFV. Fot the 30th anniversary, the event will be especially great, with the main theme being &amp;ldquo;Sustainability and Perspectives for the Brazilian Agriculture&amp;rdquo;. Certainly, there will be much interesting discussion around the latest Brazilian agricultural census that has just been released, and plenty of other interesting topics related to the future of Brazilian agriculture.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two Incredibly Useful Taylor Expansions</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/twotaylorexpansions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2018 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/twotaylorexpansions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A &amp;ldquo;Taylor expansions&amp;rdquo; is a polynomial that approximates a function in a small vicinity of a single point. They are exceptionally useful: in general, we are pretty good at solving problems involving polynomials and pretty rubbish at solving problems involving pretty much anything else. Here, we show you two elegant Taylor expansions that keep showing up here and there in different areas of research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The rule of 72</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/rule-of-72/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2018 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/rule-of-72/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;rule of 72&amp;rdquo; is &amp;ndash; or at least should be &amp;ndash; a standard tool in everyone&amp;rsquo;s mathematical toolkit, and helps us think intuitively about exponential growth and exponential decay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But did you ever stop and wonder how and why this black magic incantation actually works?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Phd Thesis Won an Award</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/phd-thesis-award/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/phd-thesis-award/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On wednesday last week, the winners of the awards (one per field) for &lt;a href=&#34;http://capes.gov.br/sala-de-imprensa/noticias/8592-premio-capes-seleciona-melhores-teses-defendidas-em-2016&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;best PhD theses in Brazil in 2016 were announced&lt;/a&gt;. And, lo and behold, there was &lt;a href=&#34;http://capes.gov.br/images/stories/download/legislacao/Portaria-199-Premio-Capes-de-Tese-2017.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;my name in the official gazette&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; receiving the award in the field of economics for my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iantrotter.com/files/Thesis_Ian_Trotter.pdf&#34;&gt;thesis on energy and climate change&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Website Launched!</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/website-launch/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2017 09:09:02 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/website-launch/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to my researcher profile website! This site will showcase my research, showing both results and work in progress. It feels a little empty at the moment, but it will gradually fill up with interesting content.
The site was hacked together in a relatively short time using the following components:
 Built with Hugo Using the Academic theme Hosted on GitHub Pages  </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>