<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Ian Michael Trotter</title>
    <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Ian Michael Trotter</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Ian Michael Trotter</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://www.iantrotter.com/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>30th International Seminar on Economic Policy</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/xxx-sipe/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Aug 2018 10:45:46 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/xxx-sipe/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m on the organising committee of the 30th International Seminar on Economic Policy (SIPE), the 13th and 14th of September, 2018. SIPE is an annual event at the Department of Agricultural Economics, UFV. Fot the 30th anniversary, the event will be especially great, with the main theme being &amp;ldquo;Sustainability and Perspectives for the Brazilian Agriculture&amp;rdquo;. Certainly, there will be much interesting discussion around the latest Brazilian agricultural census that has just been released, and plenty of other interesting topics related to the future of Brazilian agriculture.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Multidimensional Failure</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/multidimensional-failure/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Aug 2018 09:51:39 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/multidimensional-failure/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When doing research &amp;ndash; venturing into the great unknown &amp;ndash; one does not always know if one&amp;rsquo;s ideas will work out or not. I think it is inevitable that one spends time pursuing and nurturing some idea that, in the very end, turns out not to be so good. Or downright terrible, in some cases. Although some may not find this kind of thing worthy to discuss, maybe a small note here could help some other researcher avoid wasting their precious time and coming to the same dead end. So here&amp;rsquo;s a little story of my failed idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SDP&#43;QC: A Short Progress Report</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/serra-progress-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Aug 2018 13:38:58 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/serra-progress-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The research project on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iantrotter.com/project/reverse-the-curse/&#34;&gt;quantum computing and stochastic dynamic optimisation&lt;/a&gt; is just hitting its stride, and we&amp;rsquo;re getting closer to showing some very exciting results!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project is well underway &amp;ndash; about halfway through its planned course &amp;ndash; so it&amp;rsquo;s about time to take stock and see where this is going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reinforcements are Coming!</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/reinforcements/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jul 2018 16:20:26 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/reinforcements/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As part of my research project on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iantrotter.com/project/reverse-the-curse/&#34;&gt;stochastic dynamic programming and quantum computing&lt;/a&gt;, I find myself having to do a lot of heavy calculations lately. Waiting anxiously for a long time for a new set of results (or waiting to find out that the calculation just failed spectacularly) is one of the least enjoyable aspects of this kind of research. In an attempt to reduce this to a minimum, I decided to splash out on a brand new workstation &amp;ndash; hopefully it will make me a much more productive and efficient researcher!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic Dynamic Optimisation Reading List</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/sdp-literature/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jun 2018 15:39:09 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/sdp-literature/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As part of my project on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iantrotter.com/project/reverse-the-curse/&#34;&gt;stochastic dynamic optimisation&lt;/a&gt;, I am knee-deep in good literature on the subject. So here is some literature that I recommend for getting acquainted with the subject. Some are research articles of particular note, and some are textbooks &amp;ndash; but they should all be accessible to someone at an advanced undergraduate level and above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Workshop on Stochastic Dynamic Optimisation</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/sdp-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jun 2018 12:07:01 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/sdp-workshop/</guid>
      <description>As part of my research project on quantum computing and stochastic dynamic optimisation, I have invited a small number of researchers to a workshop to talk about stochastic dynamic optimisation.
If anybody reading this would like to join the workshop, please don&amp;rsquo;t hesitate to reach out.
If two heads are better than one, then just imagine how great a roomful of research scientists must be!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Testing the Julia Programming Language</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/julia/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 May 2018 15:15:02 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/julia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been hearing a lot about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://julialang.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Julia programming language&lt;/a&gt; lately. And what I&amp;rsquo;ve been hearing is basically that it is &amp;ldquo;(nearly) as fast as C/C++&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;as easy as Python&amp;rdquo;. Since my research relies heavily on computations, I thought it might be good to try using it in my project on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iantrotter.com/project/reverse-the-curse/&#34;&gt;stochastic dynamic optimisation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does it fit the bill?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Serrapilheira Event in Rio</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/serrapilheira-event/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2018 06:03:53 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/serrapilheira-event/</guid>
      <description>Instituto Serrapilheira has invited all their grantees from their first call to an event in Rio de Janeira this week. It is a great opportunity to meet young, talented scientists from all over Brazil.
The Instituto Serrapilheira has very generously sponsored my project about stochastic dynamic optimisation, and I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to finally meeting the people behind it. Not only does the institute fund scientific research projects, but I really like their focus on both diversity and open science &amp;ndash; values that personally appeal to me.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two Incredibly Useful Taylor Expansions</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/twotaylorexpansions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2018 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/twotaylorexpansions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A &amp;ldquo;Taylor expansions&amp;rdquo; is a polynomial that approximates a function in a small vicinity of a single point. They are exceptionally useful: in general, we are pretty good at solving problems involving polynomials and pretty rubbish at solving problems involving pretty much anything else. Here, we show you two elegant Taylor expansions that keep showing up here and there in different areas of research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Everything is a Stochastic Dynamic Optimisation Problem!</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/everything-is-sdp/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2018 21:59:23 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/everything-is-sdp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Stochastic dynamic optimisation problems are everywhere &amp;ndash; quite simply because most of the choices we make have consequences in the future, and incorporate some uncertainty: this means that the decision process needs to take into account not only whatever happens at the moment that the decision is made, but also how it may impact future decisions. These are common characteristics of real-world problems &amp;ndash; and all such problems present a great opportunity to study the art and science of stochastic dynamic optimisation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The rule of 72</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/rule-of-72/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2018 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/rule-of-72/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;rule of 72&amp;rdquo; is &amp;ndash; or at least should be &amp;ndash; a standard tool in everyone&amp;rsquo;s mathematical toolkit, and helps us think intuitively about exponential growth and exponential decay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But did you ever stop and wonder how and why this black magic incantation actually works?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kicking Off the Research Project on Stochastic Dynamic Optimisation</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/serra-start/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Feb 2018 09:07:06 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/serra-start/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are now in the process of starting up the research project &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iantrotter.com/project/reverse-the-curse/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Reverse the Curse: Can Quantum Computing Lift Bellman’s Curse of Dimensionality?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, which received financial support from &lt;a href=&#34;https://serrapilheira.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Instituto Serrapilheira&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Phd Thesis Won an Award</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/phd-thesis-award/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/phd-thesis-award/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On wednesday last week, the winners of the awards (one per field) for &lt;a href=&#34;http://capes.gov.br/sala-de-imprensa/noticias/8592-premio-capes-seleciona-melhores-teses-defendidas-em-2016&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;best PhD theses in Brazil in 2016 were announced&lt;/a&gt;. And, lo and behold, there was &lt;a href=&#34;http://capes.gov.br/images/stories/download/legislacao/Portaria-199-Premio-Capes-de-Tese-2017.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;my name in the official gazette&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; receiving the award in the field of economics for my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iantrotter.com/files/Thesis_Ian_Trotter.pdf&#34;&gt;thesis on energy and climate change&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Website Launched!</title>
      <link>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/website-launch/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2017 09:09:02 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iantrotter.com/post/website-launch/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to my researcher profile website! This site will showcase my research, showing both results and work in progress. It feels a little empty at the moment, but it will gradually fill up with interesting content.
The site was hacked together in a relatively short time using the following components:
 Built with Hugo Using the Academic theme Hosted on GitHub Pages  </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>